Guide to the Oliver Ellsworth Daggett Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Oliver Ellsworth Daggett Papers
1826-1880
RG 114
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(8 boxes)
Record books, sermons, writings, and notes document Daggett's ministry and his education and teaching at Yale. Oliver Ellsworth Daggett (1810-1880) served as a Congregational clergyman in Connecticut and New York from 1837 to 1877. He was Chittenden Professor of Divinity and college pastor at Yale from 1867 to 1870.
Daggett, O. E. (Oliver Ellsworth), 1810-1880
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1810 Born in New Haven, Connecticut
1828 B.A., Yale College
1834 B.D. Yale Divinity School
1837-1843 Minister at South Church, Hartford, Connecticut
1845-1867 Minister at First Congregational Church, Canandaigua, New York
1853 D.D., Hamilton College
1867-1870 Chittendon Professor of Divinity and college pastor at Yale
1871-1877 Minister at Second Congregational Church, New London, Connecticut
1872-1880 Fellow, Yale College
1877-1880 Resident of Hartford, Connecticut
1880 Died
Scope and Contents
This record group provides thorough documentation of the career of a prominent Yale-trained Congregational clergyman of the nineteenth century. Systematic registers of sermons preached and services performed are available, as well as more than 350 full sermons manuscripts and more than 1400 sermon outlines. Notes from Daggett's students years at Yale and sermons from his years as college pastor provide insight into the religious climate at the University.
Arrangement
I. Record Books, 1832-1875
II. Sermons, Addresses, and Writings, 1833-1876, n.d.
III. Notes and Notebooks, 1826-1880
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1872, n.d.
Clergy; Daggett, O. E. (Oliver Ellsworth), 1810-1880; Yale University -- Religion
- Record Books, 1832-1875; Series I
  - Register of sermon manuscripts: No. 1-361; first delivered 1832-1875. Title and text of sermon listed by Daggett's numbering system with locations and dates preached indicated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Register of sermon outlines ("extemporaneous or unwritten sermons"): No. 1-1420; register begun in 183, undated towards end. Title and text of sermon outlines listed by a separate numbering sequence; some locations and dates indicated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Register of Sabbaths and other services: 1833-1880; chronological record of Daggett's preaching activities indicating location and number of sermon manuscript or outline used. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Register of official services in the Church of Christ in Yale College during pastorate of Daggett: 1867 Oct. 31 to 1870 Jul. 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Sermons, Addresses, and Writings, 1833-1876, n.d.; Series II
  - Sermon manuscripts
    - Numbered according to Daggett's system: 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
    - No. 16-76 (Box 2, Folder 9-18)
    - No. 77-163 (Box 3, Folder 19-29)
    - No. 164-234 (Box 4, Folder 30-39)
    - No. 235-307 (Box 5, Folder 40-49)
    - No. 308-360; three unnumbered sermons (Box 6, Folder 50-57)
  - Sermon outlines
    - Numbered according to Daggett's system: No. 1-119 (Box 6, Folder 58-59)
    - No. 201-1000 (Box 7, Folder 60-67)
    - No. 1001-1419 (Box 8, Folder 68-72)
  - Lectures and Addresses
    - Address at the laying of the cornerstone of the Plymouth Church of Rochester., Sept. 8, 1833 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - American Poetry, March 22, 1843 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Address to pupils of Canandaigua Academy, July 1, 1845 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Address to pupils of Ontario Female Seminary, June 10, 1846 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - The Authority of Civil Government, July 3, 1846 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Major Andre, February 9, 1854 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Address at Bernis Hall, January 18, 1855 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - The Model Young Man, December 24, 1857 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Ladies and Gentlemen, February 1, 1859 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - The Seer in the Seen, March 1, 1860 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Address at the funeral of Captain Chas. M. Wheeler, July 26, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - A Charge to the People, May 9, 1865 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Address on the 200th anniversary of the first church in New London, Connecticut, October 19, 1870 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Address at Mr. Haven's funeral, May 3, 1876 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Dreams, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Spiritualism, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Articles and exposition of Biblical texts
    - The Permanent and the Temporary in Scripture (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Because of the Angels (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - An Exegesis of Acts 26:28 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - An Interpretation of Acts 26:28 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - An Exposition of Ephesians (Box 9, Folder 77)
- Notes, 1826-1880; Series III
  - Volume containing "Lectures of Prof. Olmstead on Natural Philosophy" and "Quotations from Prose and Poetry and Remarks of living persons", 1826-1827 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - "Disputes" on various questions, 1826-1828 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Lecture notes: arranged chronologically, 1851-1880 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Notes for Bible classes, 1838, 1847 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Notes Related to Psalms and Hymns (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Notes regarding "Percentage of Professors of Religion" (Box 9, Folder 82)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1872, n.d; Series IV
  - Statistics of pastorates of OED (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - List of OED articles in the Independent (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Form of service for extension of "Right Hand of Fellowship" (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Copy of letter written by former prisoner to friend still in prison, 1872 (Box 9, Folder 83)